Guide to the François-Jules Harmand papers, 1845-1956
Harmand, François-Jules papers, 1845-1956
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
François-Jules Harmand papers, 1845-1956, 1845-1922 (bulk).
3481
François-Jules Harmand, 1845-1921.
4.7 cubic ft.
Correspondence, diaries, research materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Personal and official correspondence; autobiographical notes and diaries; medical reports concerning French Navy personnel; photographs; diplomatic reports; archaeological, botanical, and ethnographic accounts concerning Southeast Asia and its people; and documents pertaining to the Tonkin expedition (1873) led by Francis Garnier, in which Harmand participated, including numerous maps and drawings, some by Harmand, reports and journals, and a genealogical table of the Vietnamese royal family Nguyêñ. Speeches, military intelligence reports and maps, and contemporary copies of the Annamite Proclamation of June 8, 1883, and the Ultimatum of the Convention of Hué (1883) with Harmand's commentary; also included are reports concerning political, economic, and social conditions and a proposal for establishing a French telegraphic line; letters, which Harmand acquired while consul in Bangkok, to M. Blancheton, an earlier French consul to Siam, from the French trader and explorer, Jean Dupuis, who was also a member of the Garnier expedition, and notes detailing the development of French interest and influence in Southeast Asia (author, unknown, n.d.) are included. Additional diplomatic documents consist of photographs and dispatches concerning military affairs and cultural traditions in India (1885-1890); a photograph album and dispatches both sent and received while Minister Plenipotentiary to Japan (1894-1906);
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
François-Jules Harmand was a physician in the French Navy, natural scientist, Commissioner of the Republic to Vietnam and Laos and consul to Thailand, India, Chile, and Minister Plenipotentiary to Japan.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Personal and official correspondence; autobiographical notes and diaries; medical reports concerning French Navy personnel; photographs; diplomatic reports; archaeological, botanical, and ethnographic accounts concerning Southeast Asia and its people; and documents pertaining to the Tonkin expedition (1873) led by Francis Garnier, in which Harmand participated, including numerous maps and drawings, some by Harmand, reports and journals, and a genealogical table of the Vietnamese royal family Nguyêñ. Speeches, military intelligence reports and maps, and contemporary copies of the Annamite Proclamation of June 8, 1883, and the Ultimatum of the Convention of Hué (1883) with Harmand's commentary; also included are reports concerning political, economic, and social conditions and a proposal for establishing a French telegraphic line; letters, which Harmand acquired while consul in Bangkok, to M. Blancheton, an earlier French consul to Siam, from the French trader and explorer, Jean Dupuis, who was also a member of the Garnier expedition, and notes detailing the development of French interest and influence in Southeast Asia (author, unknown, n.d.) are included. Additional diplomatic documents consist of photographs and dispatches concerning military affairs and cultural traditions in India (1885-1890); a photograph album and dispatches both sent and received while Minister Plenipotentiary to Japan (1894-1906)
a proposal and accompanying letter (ca. 1900) in English by Sun Yat-sen requesting support for an effort to free southern China from Manchu dynastic rule; and a few letters discussing events in Chile (1890-1891) and efforts to aid Russians imprisoned in Japan (1904-1905). Also included are newspaper clippings concerning political and scientific interest and activities; diplomas, certificates, and a record of his military service; and documents regarding the donation of his library to the University of Strasbourg. Additional correspondents include L. Pierre, a personal friend, members of the family of Francis Garnier, Admiral Marie-Jules Dupré, Admiral Peyron, General Alexandre-Eugene Bouët (1833-1887), Sir John Strachey (1823-1907), Alexandre E.J. Yersin (1860-1943), and Dr. H. Vergniaud, a fellow participant in the Garnier expedition. The papers are primarily in French and Southeast Asian languages.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Harmand, François-Jules,1845-1921.; Blancheton, M.; Bouët, Alexandre-Eugene, 1833-1887.; Dupré, Marie-Jules,; Dupuis, Jean.; Garnier family.; Garnier, Francis, 1839-1873.; Nguyêñ family.; Peyron,; Pierre, L.; Strachey, John, 1823-1907.; Sun, Yat-sen, 1866-1925.; Vergniaud, H.; Yersin, Alexandre E.J., 1860-1943.; France.Marine.; University of Strasbourg.
Subjects:
Manchus.
Places:
Chile.; China--History.; Siam.; India.; France--Foreign Relations--1870-1940.; Asia, Southeastern--History.; Vietnam--History--1858-1945.; Vietnam--Civilization--European influences.; Japan.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.2aat
INFORMATION FOR USERS
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Personal Papers
Series II. Explorations in Southeast Asia
Series III. Work on Natural History in France
Series IV. Consular appointment in Siam
Series V. Consul General's appointment to Calcutta, India
Series VI. Assignment to Chile
Series VII. Sojourn in Japan
Series VIII. Activities after his retirement in France
Series IX. Maps and Documents
CONTAINER LIST
- Personal Papers, 1862-1922
  - Autobiographical notes, 1866-08-03 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Birth Certificate, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Personal, military, and professional certificates, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Handwritten report of his military activities describing 10 years along with medical records, Date Unknown (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Two letters, 1883-05-29; Pierre, M. L.; Mme. Harmand (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Harmand, Francois-Jules
    Mme. Harmand
    Pierre, M. L.
    Saigon
  - Letters and a newspaper clipping, 1902-01-13 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Garnier, Francis
    St. Etienne
  - Letters and a notebook listing books of Harmand, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    University of Strasbourg
  - Diplomatic appointments and certificates, Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Letters of introduction and recommendation, Undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Diplomas, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Certificates from academic societies, Undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Paper for the Medal of the Royal Court of Merit of Cambodia, 1907-04-13 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Set of cards on various subjects, Undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Covers wood, mushrooms, textiles, rice, etc.
  - Set of cards on various subjects, Undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Handwritten notes and a typewritten biography, Undated; d'Hangouwart, Lieutenant-Colonel (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photos, 1862-1921 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Necrology, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Explorations in Southeast Asia, 1866-1883
  - Notebook and cards with notes, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Notebook with loose notes, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Notebook with loose notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Travel report, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Notes and maps, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letters of introduction, Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Travel Reports, 1876; Vergniaud, H. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Notes, 1875-05-1875-06 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Notes, 1875-11-1875-12 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Notes, 1876-01-1876-05 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Notes, 1877-02-1877-04 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Notes, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Two notebooks with nautical annotations and drawings, 1875-1877 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Notes, 1877-01-09-1877-01-31 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Language studies with archaeological drawings, Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Photos and Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Report to the French Governor, 1876-1877 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Dupre, Admiral
  - Report to the Minister of Education, Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Notes from a zoological report to a minister, 1876-04 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Report to the director of a museum of natural history, 1876-04-20 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Incomplete report, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Notebook containing copies of telegrams, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Notebook containing copies of telegrams, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Notebook with drawings and loose notes, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Used for anthropological and ethnographic studies
  - Anthropological notebook, Undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Zoological photos and drawings, Undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Notebooks of zoological notes, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Genealogical table of the Vietnamese Royal Family, Nguyen, Undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Nguyen
  - Letters, 1873-1874; Dupuis, Jean (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Blancheton
    Siam
  - Correspondence, 1870-1876 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence, 1877-1881 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Work on Natural History in France, 1869-1881
  - Fragmentary notes about the organization of Indochina, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Report on a projected railroad in Southeast Asia, 1877-04-04 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Report on proposed business school for Indo-Chinese in Paris, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Report about the Island de Khong, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Report to M. Milnes- Edwards, scientific representative of the French government. Attached is a proposal for a trip to Indochina, 1881-07; M. Milnes-Edwards (Box 2, Folder 5)
    France
    Indochina
  - Report on administration of the colonies, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - A confidential report by Harmand for an economic and scientific dictionary, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Notes - "Indochinese Races" with pencil drawings, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Notes for a lecture, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Instructions for missionaries going to Vietnam, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Vietnam
  - General notes about Vietnam, products, sketches, etc., Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous notes and a notebook about Vietnam, Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Notes from a conference, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Description of rice culture, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Photos of rice paddies, Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Photos of indigenous population, Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - A notebook and a bibliography on Indochina, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Consular appointment in Siam, 1881-1885
  - Military reports and hand-drawn maps, Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Report on the installation of a French telegraph line, Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Notes concerning the border between Siam and Cambodia, Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Receipts, Undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Various Notes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Administrative documents and recommendations, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Bangkok
  - A report concerning the French-Siamese question, Undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - A report concerning the political interests of France and England in Siam and Burma, 1885 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Paris, France
  - Notes documenting the French interest and influence in Siam, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Reprint of Indochinese Affairs, 1884 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Report about border conflicts, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Contemporary copy of the Convention of Hue and comments concerning it, 1883-08-23 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Journals, 1881-1882 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Journals, 1882-1883 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Notes about unrest in Tonkin, 1881-1883 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Conference, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Annam
    Tonkin
  - Notes about Cambodia, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Various undated notes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Notes by Colonel Laurent about Tonkin, annotated by Harmand, 1883-01-09 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Memoirs written by M. de Beaumont annotated by Harmand, 1882-1883 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Official documents in Thai concerning regulations of the French government and letters of introduction, Undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - 1881 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - January-July 1882, 1882-01-1882-07 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - August-September 1882, 1882-08-1882-09 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - October-December 1882, 1882-10-1882-12 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - A notebook with non-official correspondence, 1882-1883 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - January-March 1883, 1883-01-1883-03 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - April-July 1883, 1883-04-1883-07 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - August-September 1883, 1883-08-1883-09 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - October-December 1883, 1883-10-1883-12 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Undated letters, 1881-1883 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Consul General's appointment to Calcutta, India, 1884-1890
  - Report on the organization of French-Indochina, 1885 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Report on communication in French-Indochina, 1885 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Military report by M. de Torey discussing occupation, 1886 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Report on boundaries, Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Report on the organization of Annam, 1885 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Report on French military forces on Indochina, 1885 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Report on carbon mines in Tonkin, Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Notes on Indian government, Undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Notes on administration in the French colonies, Undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Notes on special affairs in Indochina and a newspaper clipping describing Harmand's opinion, 1885-04-01-1885-04-02 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    National
  - Notes discussing various issues, including border problems with China, Undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Notes, possibly a draft for a letter, Undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - A letter by M. Fontaine discussing navigable waterways, 1890 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Photos, Undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Photos, Undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - A journal and notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Notes on a book by Sir John Strachey, translated by Harmand, Undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - January-June 1884, 1884-01-1884-06 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - July-December 1884, 1884-07-1884-12 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - 1885 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - 1886 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - 1887 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - 1888 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - 1889 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - 1890 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Assignment to Chile, 1890, undated
  - Official letter from the foreign ministry sending Harmand to Chile, Undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Papers concerning the retirement of M. de Bacourt, Undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, 1890 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - 1884-1893 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Sojourn in Japan, 1890-1906
  - Journal on diplomatic affairs, 1894-1895 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Telegrams, 1894-1899 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Telegrams, 1900-1901 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Telegrams, 1902-1905 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Telegrams, 1905-1906 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Treaty of August 4, 1896 between France and Japan with various notes, 1896-08-04 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Notes about organization in Vietnam and Laos with two notebooks, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Copy of report of the French Consul in Canton, 1894-12 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Handwritten notes relating to the French-Siamese conflict, 1893-1894 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Reprint from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and newspaper clippings, 1893-1894 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Three reports by Yersin to the Governor-General, 1893 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Various letters, notes, and reprints relating to Yersin and photographs taken by Yersin, 1892-1894 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Letters from Yersin to Harmand, 1895-1900 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Japan
  - An album with photos taken by Alex Halot, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Notes and reprints with cards on various subjects, 1890 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - 1891-1893 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - 1894 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - 1895 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - 1896-1898 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - 1899-1900 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - 1900-1906 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Activities after his retirement in France
  - Newspaper clippings, 1910-1911 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Reviews of his publications, 1910-1912 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1907-1922 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Undated material, Undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Maps and Documents, 1875-1883
  - Collection Description, Undated (Box 6)
  - Sala Royal painting, Undated (Box 6)
  - Border Between Siam and the Providence of Tenasserim, 1881 (Box 6)
  - Southeast Asia, annotated, 1879 (Box 6)
  - Itinerary in Indo-China for Dr. Harmand, 1875-1877 (Box 6)
  - Bassac, La Khon and Hue, annotated, 1877 (Box 6)
  - L'Isthme de Kra, 1881-08-14 (Box 6)
  - Convention de Hue, 1883-04-25 (Box 6)